CHAPTER 2

Caste and Annihilation of Caste

INTRODUCTION

In this chapter, we have discussed Ambedkar’s views on varna and individual’s place in varna, the origin of caste and the question of annihilation of caste. Ambedkar has engaged with the structure of Indian society in great detail. He has emphasized that this structure is based on the ‘individual’ and his place in varna. Theoretically, this is a very significant sociological proposition that has not been highlighted by various social scientists and sociologists. Ambedkar is of the opinion that the Hindu social order does not recognize the existence of individuals that are part of a larger group called varna (a division of the society into four classes—Brahmins, Kshtriyas, Vaishyas and Shudras). The varna is a hierarchically arranged system with unequal rights and privileges. Because of this hierarchical arrangement of varnas, with unequal rights and privileges, the Hindu social order lacks the principles of equality, liberty and fraternity and, hence, democracy.

Apart from varna, this chapter also discusses Ambedkar’s theory of genesis, mechanism and development of caste. We have probed how he has refuted the theories of the origin of caste as propounded by various European social thinkers and then how he has propounded his own thesis regarding the origin of caste in Indian society. Further, in this context, we have also discussed the mechanism through which the caste has developed and spread in every nook and corner of the Indian society. Last, but not the least, Ambedkar has not only given the structure of varna and the mechanism of caste, but has also propounded his thesis and the scheme to annihilate the caste system.

In doing so, Ambedkar challenged the social reforms practiced by different socio-political forces of his time. Ambedkar analysed the nature and quality of social reforms as proposed by the then Congress, Socialists, and Arya Samajis (an organization of Hindus who believed in the Vedas in its pristine and pure state). He outrightly rejected them all because, in his opinion, they all could not understand the problem, but gave very shallow remedies to annihilate the caste system. Against the lopsided and petty reforms suggested by other forces, Ambedkar propounded philosophically and theoretically very radical reforms in the Hindu social order for the annihilation of caste.

To begin with, he argued that if one has to annihilate caste, then

I am convinced that the real remedy is inter-marriage. Fusion of blood can alone create the feelings of being kith and kin, and unless this feeling of being kindred, becomes paramount the separatist feeling—the feeling of being aliens-created by caste will not vanish. . . . The real remedy for breaking caste is inter-marriage. Nothing else will serve as the solvent of caste (Ambedkar 1979: 67).

The second proposition of annihilation of caste as proposed by Ambedkar is,

The real remedy is to destroy the belief in the sanctity of Shastra. . . . You must, therefore, destroy the sacredness and divinity with which caste has become invested . . . this means you must destroy the authority of the Shastras and Vedas (sacred texts of Hindus) (Ambedkar 1979: 68-9).

The third method to annihilate caste was the abolition of priesthood by one caste (ibid.); rather, he suggested that priests should be servants of the state. Further, I draw an inference from Ambedkar’s argument, which is not latently related to the annihilation of caste; that is, he opined that,

. . . the priesthood must at least cease to be hereditary. Every person who professes to be Hindu must be eligible for being a priest. It should be provided by law . . . and holds a Sanad from the state. . . . (Ambedkar 1979: 77).

In this way, this chapter will present a comprehensive picture of the caste system as envisaged and analysed by Ambedkar. We have observed that, usually, social scientists analyse caste as an independent unit. However, according to Ambedkar, if we have to understand caste, then we have to understand Hindu social structure as well. Hindu social structure comprises varna in a hierarchical order. He treats varna as class. Moreover, varnas are further divided into castes because of the imposition of exogamy over endogamy. He refutes the occupational, racial, and communal theory of the genesis of caste. Last but not the least, he gives his proposition of annihilation of caste.

AMBEDKAR’S PERSPECTIVE ON CASTE

Ambedkar drew attention to the rigidity of the caste system and its essential features. Graded inequality is the fundamental principle on which caste is based. That is beyond doubt, Ambedkar emphasized. According to him,

The four classes are not only different but also unequal in status; one stands above the other. In the scheme of Manu, the Brahmin occupies the uppermost rank, followed by the Kshatriya, Vaishya, and Shudra. Below the Shudra is ati-Shudra, or the untouchable. This order of precedence among the classes is not merely conventional. It is spiritual, moral and legal. There is no sphere of life that is not regulated by this principle of graded inequality (Ambedkar 1987(c): 107).

Further, Ambedkar has also highlighted the fact that, ‘The principle of graded inequality has been carried into the economic field’ (ibid.: 111). The Hindu social order does not recognize, ‘From each according to his ability; to each according to his needs’. It favours the distribution of the good things of life among those who are reckoned as the highest in the social hierarchy.

The second principle on which the Hindu social order is founded is that of prescribed graded occupations that are inherited from father to son for each class. In other words, it can be termed as ‘fixity of occupations for each class and continuance by heredity’ (ibid.). The third feature of the Hindu social order, according to Ambedkar, is the confinement of interaction of people to their respective groups instead of inter-dining and inter-marriages, between people of different classes. According to Ambedkar, there is nothing strange or peculiar that the Hindu social order recognizes classes. There are classes everywhere, and no society exists without them; even a free social order will not be able to get rid of the classes completely. A free social order, however, aims to prevent isolation and exclusiveness because it prevents the members of the class from becoming inimical towards one another (Ambedkar 1987(c): 113).

(a) INTERPRETATION OF VARNA THEORY

Ambedkar recognized the existence of four varnas in the Hindu social order. He emphasized that the Hindu social order is primarily based on the class (varna) and not on individuals. He opined that the unit of Hindu society is neither the individual Brahmin, nor the individual Kshatriya, Vaishya, Shudra, or the Untouchables. Even the family is not regarded, in the Hindu social order, as a unit of society except for the purposes of marriage and inheritance. The unit of Hindu society is the class (varna). In the Hindu social order, there is no room for individual merit and no consideration of individual justice. If a person has a privilege, it is not because it is due to him/her as an individual. The privilege goes with the class, and if he/she is found to enjoy it, it is because he/she belongs to that class. Conversely, an individual suffers not because he/she deserves it by virtue of his/ her conduct; rather, it is because he/she belongs to that class. Ambedkar analysed the impact of the division of society into varnas in the Hindu social order. He argued that because of this division, the Hindu social order has failed to uphold the values of liberty, equality and fraternity—the three essentials of a free social order. The Hindus do believe that God created different classes of people from different parts of his divine body. According to Ambedkar (1987(c): 100)

The doctrine that the different classes were created from different parts of the divine body has generated the belief that it must be divine will that they should remain separate and distinct. It is this belief that has created in the Hindu an instinct to be different, to be separate and to be distinct from the rest of his fellow Hindus.

In the same vein, Ambedkar adds that

The most extensive and wild manifestation of this spirit of isolation and separation is of course the caste-system. . . . Originally, there were four only. Today, how many are there? It is estimated that the total is not less than 2,000. It must be 3,000. . . . Castes are divided into sub-castes (Ambedkar, 1987(c): 102).

The question that Ambedkar raised is, ‘What fraternity can there be in a social order based upon such sentiments?’ Ambedkar asks, ‘Does the Hindu social order recognize equality?’ He underlines that while the Hindu social order accepts that men have come from the body of the creator of the universe, it does not treat them as equal because they were created from the different parts of his body that are themselves graded in terms of perceived importance and locations. The Brahmins were created from the mouth, the Kshatriyas from the arms, the Vaishyas from his thighs and the Shudras from the feet. Ambedkar agrees with natural endowments, as he opined that the Hindu social order, refuses to recognize that men no matter how profoundly they differ as individuals in capacity and character, are equally entitled as human beings to consideration and respect, and that the well-being of a society is likely to be increased if it plans its organization that, whether their powers are great or small, all its members may be equally enabled to make the best of such powers as they possess (Ambedkar 1987(c): 106).

It is for this reason he feels that the Hindu social order is against the ‘equalitarian temper’, and does not allow equality of circumstances, institutions and lifestyles to develop. In the same context, Ambedkar upholds that there is an absence of liberty, specifically ‘liberty of action’, in the Hindu social order because the occupation and status of the individuals are all fixed on the basis of their birth in a particular family. The same is true for political liberty as well. The Hindu social order does not recognize the necessity of a representative government chosen by the people. According to him, though the Hindu social order does recognize that laws must govern the people, it negates the idea that the laws can be made by the representatives chosen by the people. Ambedkar submits that the Hindus are of the opinion that the laws by which people are to be governed already exist in the Vedas, and no human being is empowered to bring about a change in the existing laws (Ambedkar 1987(c): 114). In the absence of equality and liberty, there is no fraternity in the Hindu social order. In this context, Ambedkar asks the question, ‘Does the Hindu social order recognize fraternity?’ and then goes on to demonstrate that fraternity does not exist in the Hindu society.

To demonstrate the aforementioned fact, Ambedkar took a survey of Hindu social structure and its philosophy. According to him,

The Hindus . . . do believe that men are created by God . . . But . . . God created different men from different parts of his divine body . . . and therefore. . . . The Brahmin is no brother of the Kshatriya because the former is born from the mouth of the divinity while the latter is from the arms. The Kshatriya is no brother of the Vaishya because the former is born from the arms and the latter from the thighs. As no one is a brother to the other, no one is the keeper of the other’ (Ambedkar 1987(c): 100).

Further, Ambedkar substantiated his argument ‘why there is no fraternity among Hindus’ by arguing that

. . . the doctrine that the classes (varnas) were created from different parts of the Divine body has generated the belief that it must be divine will that they should remain separate and distinct. It is this belief that has created in Hindus an instinct to be different, to be separated and to be distinct from the rest of his fellow Hindus. . . . It is also the Hindu instinct due to the same belief never to overlook a difference if it does exist but to emphasize it, recognize it, and to blaze it forth (Ambedkar 1987(c): 100-101).

The caste system is the best example of such instinct, which emphasizes, recognizes and blazes the difference between different castes. According to Ambedkar,

The most extensive and wild manifestation of this spirit of isolation and separation is, of course, the caste-system. . . . Originally there were four castes only. Today . . . It might be 3000. This is not the only staggering aspect of this fact. There are others. Castes are divided into sub-castes . . . (For e.g.) . . . The total population of the Brahmin Caste is about a crore and a half. But there are 1886 sub-castes . . . there are 1886 sub-castes of Brahmin caste!! In Punjab alone, the Saraswat Brahmins are divided into 469 sub-castes. The Kayastha’s of Punjab are divided into 890 sub-castes’ (Ambedkar 1987(c): 100-102).

If the Hindu society is so-deeply fragmented on the lines of varna, castes and sub-castes, then what is the social impact on the groups and individuals who constitute it? On this, Ambedkar argues that the impact is,

. . . infinite process of splitting social life into small fragments. The splitting process has made a social life quite impossible. . . . Their guiding principle is ‘be separate’, ‘do not intermarry, do not inter-dine’ and ‘do not touch’ . . . Far from working in a spirit of fraternity the mutual relations of the castes are fratricidal . . . (for instance) . . . there has been . . . a class war between Brahmans and Kshatriyas that lasted for several generations and which was fought so hard and with such virulence that it turned out to be a war of extermination. It must not be supposed that the fratricidal spirit has given place to a spirit of fratricity. The same spirit of separation marks the Hindu Social order today. This is best illustrated by the rules of hyper commensality and the rules of hypergamy . . . (which are) spirit of high and low (Ibid.).

Hence, he concluded that ‘The Hindu Social order is a ladder of castes placed one above the other together are representing the ascending scale of hatred and the descending scale of contempt’ (ibid.: 105). Therefore, one can easily argue that the Hindu Social order lacks fraternity.

(b) GENESIS OF CASTE SYSTEM

After defining the Hindu social order comprising varna in a hierarchical pattern, Ambedkar proposed his theory of the origin of caste as well. To propound his own theory of the genesis of the caste system in India, Ambedkar first analysed the definitions of caste as proposed in India by Senart, Nesfield, Risley, and Ketkar closely. According to Senart, Ambedkar opined that

a caste is a close corporation, in theory at any rate rigorously hereditary; equipped with a certain traditional and independent organization, including a chief and a council meeting on occasion in assemblies of more or less plenary authority and joining together at certain festivals: bound together by common occupation, which relate more particularly to marriage and food and to questions of ceremonial pollution, and ruling its members by the exercise of jurisdiction, the extent of which varies, but which succeeds in making the authority of the community more felt by the sanction of certain penalties and above all by final irrevocable exclusion from the group’ (Ambedkar 1979: 6-7).

Further, Ambedkar also highlights that Nesfield has defined a caste as ‘a class of the community that disowns any connection with any other class and can neither intermarry nor eat nor drink with any but a person of their own community’ (ibid.: 7) Ambedkar quotes Risley, according to whom,

a caste may be defined as a collection of families or groups of families bearing a common name that usually denotes or is associated with a specific occupation, claiming common descent from a mythical ancestor, human or divine, professing to follow the same professional callings and being regarded by those who are competent to give an opinion as forming a single homogeneous community.

Finally, Ambedkar takes note of Ketkar’s definition of caste. According to Ketkar caste is,

a social group having two characteristics: (I) membership is confined to those who are born of members and includes all persons so born; (II) the members are forbidden by an inexorable social law to marry outside the group (ibid.).

Reviewing the aforementioned definitions of castes given by different social scientists, Ambedkar emphasized that most scholars have defined caste as an isolated unit, which is not correct, according to Ambedkar, because castes do not exist as an isolated unit on their own; they exist as a system.

Ambedkar analyses only those characteristics from the definitions of castes, which he regards as peculiar and of universal occurrence. For Senart, the ‘idea of pollution’ was a significant characteristic of caste. Ambedkar refuted this by arguing that by no means is it peculiar to caste. It usually originates in priestly ceremonialism and in the general belief in purity. Its connection with caste as an essential element may be ruled out because even without it, the caste system operates. He concludes that the idea of pollution is associated with caste only because priesthood and purity are old associates, and it is the priestly caste who enjoys the highest rank in the caste hierarchy. Ambedkar identified the absence of dining with those outside one’s own caste as one of the peculiar characteristics in Nesfield’s definition of caste. He points out that Nesfield had mistaken the effect for the cause. The absence of inter-dining is the effect of the caste system and not its cause. Further, Ketkar defines a caste in its relation to a system of castes. Ketkar identified two characteristics of caste: (a) prohibition of inter-marriage and (b) membership by autogeny. Ambedkar argues that these two aspects are not different because if inter-marriage is prohibited, the result is that membership is limited to those born within the group.

After critical evaluation of the various characteristics of caste as given by various thinkers, Ambedkar infers that prohibition or rather the absence of inter-marriage between people of different castes is the only viable characteristic that can be considered as the critical element of caste. Further, Ambedkar also observed that, among the Hindus, castes are endogamous, while gotras within a particular caste are exogamous. In spite of the endogamy of the castes, exogamy at the level of gotra is strictly observed. There are more rigorous penalties for those who break the laws of exogamy than for those who break the laws of endogamy. It is understandable that exogamy cannot be prescribed at the level of caste because then caste, as a definite, identifiable unit, would cease to exist. Elaborating on the same point, Ambedkar argues that preventing marriages in the group creates a problem from within the group, which is not easy to solve.

The problem is that the number of individuals of either sex is more or less evenly distributed in a normal group, and they are of similar age. If a group desires to consolidate its identity as a caste, then it has to maintain a strict balance in the number of persons belonging to either sex. Maintenance of numbers becomes the primary goal because if a group wants to reserve the practice of endogamy, it is absolutely necessary to maintain numerical equality between marriageable individuals of the two sexes within the group. Ambedkar (1979:10) concludes, ‘The problem of caste, then ultimately resolves itself into one of repairing disparity between the marriageable units of the two sexes within it.’ What naturally happens is that there is a ‘surplus’ of either sex in society. If a man dies, his wife is ‘surplus’, and if a woman dies, her husband is ‘surplus’. If the group does not take care of this surplus population, it can easily break the law of endogamy. Ambedkar argues that there are two ways in which the problem of ‘surplus women’ is resolved in society. ‘Surplus women’ may either be burnt on the funeral pyre of their deceased husbands, or strict rules of endogamy may be imposed on them. Since burning with her deceased husband is rather an impractical way of solving the problem of sex disparity, the prohibition of re-marriage is imposed on them or in other words widowhood is enforced on them.

Regarding the problem of ‘surplus men’, Ambedkar says that men have dominated society for centuries and enjoyed greater prestige than women. The same treatment, therefore, cannot be accorded to them. A widower can remain so for the rest of his life, but given the sexual desire that is natural, he is a threat to the morals of the group, particularly if he leads an active social life and not as a recluse. He has to be, therefore, allowed to marry a second time with a woman who is not previously married. This is, however, a difficult proposition. If a widower is provided a second woman, then an imbalance in the number of women of marriageable age is created. A ‘surplus man’ can, therefore, be provided a wife who has not yet reached marriageable age, i.e., a minor girl. Ambedkar identifies four means by which numerical disparity between two sexes can be dealt with—burning of the widow with her deceased husband, compulsory widowhood, imposition of celibacy on the widower, and wedding of the widower to a girl who has not yet attended marriageable age. In Hindu society, the customs of sati, prohibition of widow remarriage, and marriage of minor girls are practiced. A widower may also observe sannyasa (i.e., renounce the world). These practices take care of maintaining the numerical balance between both sexes, born out of endogamy.

For Ambedkar, the question of the spread and origin of caste are not seprated. According to Ambedkar, the caste system has either been imposed upon the docile population of India by a lawgiver as a divine dispensation, or it has developed according to some law of social growth peculiar to the Indian people. Ambedkar refutes the notion that the law of caste was given by some lawgiver. Manu is considered to exist. Even if he existed, the caste system predates Manu. No doubt Manu upheld it and philosophized about it, but he certainly did not and could not ordain the present order of Hindu society. His work ended with the confiscation of existing caste rules and the preaching of caste dharma (duties), obligations and conduct associated with each caste. Ambedkar rejects the argument that the Brahmin created the caste. He maintains that it was necessary to dismantle this belief because there still is a strong belief in the minds of orthodox Hindus that the Hindu society was molded into the framework of the caste system and that it is consciously crafted in the shastras (the sacred texts). It may be noted that the teaching and preaching of shastras are the prerogative of the Brahmins (Ambedkar 1979).

Ambedkar agrees with the second argument, i.e., of some law of social growth peculiar to Indian people about the spread of the caste system. According to Western scholars, the bases of origin of various castes in India are occupation, survival of tribal organizations, the rise of new belief systems, cross breeding and migrating (Ambedkar 1979: 17). The problem, according to Ambedkar, is that the aforesaid nuclei also exist in other societies and are not peculiar to India. Ambedkar asked, ‘. . . why is it they did not “form” caste on other parts of this planet?’ At some stage, the priestly class detached itself from the rest of the body of people and emerged as a caste by itself. The other classes that were subject to the law of social division of labour underwent differentiation. Some of these classes got divided into bigger groups and some into smaller ones. According to Ambedkar,

This sub-division of a society is quite natural. But the unnatural thing about these sub-divisions is that they have lost the open-door character of the class system and have become self-enclosed units called castes. The question is: were they compelled to close their doors and become endogamous, or did they close them of their own accord (Ambedkar 1979: 18)?

Ambedkar submitted a double line of answer,

Some closed their door: Others found it closed against them. The one is a psychological interpretation and the other is mechanistic, but they are complementary and both are necessary to explain the phenomen of caste-formation in its entirety (Ambedkar 1979: 18).

Explaining the psychological interpretation of endogamy, Ambedkar opined that endogamy was popular in the Hindu society. Since it had originated from the Brahmin caste, it was wholeheartedly imitated by all the non-Brahmin subdivisions or classes, who, in their turn, became endogamous castes. Ambedkar quotes Tarde’s law of imitation in this context. According to Tarde, ‘imitation flows from higher to lower’. Second, ‘the intensity of imitation varies inversely in proportion to distance. . . . Distance is understood here in its sociological meaning’ (Ambedkar 1979: 19).

Ambedkar (1979: 19) points out that some castes were formed by imitating others because the crucial conditions for the formation of castes by imitation existed in Hindu society. He feels that (i) that the source of imitation must enjoy prestige in the group and (ii) that there must be ‘numerous and daily relations’ among members of the group. Ambedkar opined that the Brahmin is treated as next to God in Indian society. His prestige is unquestionable, and he is the fountainhead of all that is good. He is idolized by scriptures; therefore, ‘Such a creature is worthy of more than mere imitation, but at least of imitation; and if he lives in an endogamous enclosure should not the rest follow his example?’ He argues that the imitation of non-Brahmins of those customs, which supported the structure of caste in these nascent days until it became embedded in the Hindu mind and persists even today, is testimony to the fact that imitation is the cause of the formation of caste. The customs of sati, enforced widowhood, and marriage of girls are followed in one way or the other by different castes. Ambedkar opines,

Those castes that are nearest to the Brahmin have imitated all the three customs and insist on the strict observance thereof. Those that are less near have imitated enforced widowhood and girl marriage; others, a little further off, have only girl marriage and those furthest of have imitated only the belief in the caste Principle’ (Ambedkar, 1979: 20).

ANNIHILATION OF CASTE

Ambedkar analyses the steps taken by the socialists to annihilate the caste system through economic development and reforms. He questions the wisdom of socialists who professed that acquiring economic power is the only motive by which man is actuated, and economic power is the only kind of power that one can exercise effectively over others. He opined that the social status of an individual by itself often becomes a source of power. He suggests that religion, social status, and property are all sources of power and authority that come into play into different situations. Ambedkar feels that without bringing freedom in the social order, one cannot bring about economic change. He also cautioned the socialists that the proletariat or the poor do not constitute a homogeneous category. They are divided not only on the basis of their economic situation but also on the basis of caste and creed. They cannot, therefore, unite against those who exploit them.

According to Ambedkar (1979: 46),

It seems to me that, other things being equal, the only thing that will move one man to take such an action is the feeling that other men with whom he is acting are actuated by a sense of equality, fraternity, and, above all, justice. Men will not join in a revolution for the equalization of property unless they know that after the revolution is achieved they will be treated equally and that there will be no discrimination of caste and creed. . . . The assurance must be the assurance proceeding from much deeper foundations, namely, the mental attitude of the compatriots towards one another in their spirit of personal equality and fraternity.

Seen in the above light the elimination of caste through economic reform is not tenable; hence, socialists would have to deal with hierarchy in the caste system first before effecting economic change and annihilation of caste.

After discussing the strategies of annihilation of caste by socialists, Ambedkar explains that caste is not a physical object like a wall of bricks or a line or barbed wire that prevents the Hindus from free social interaction. Caste is a notion; it is a state of the mind. If someone wants to break the caste system, he/she has to attack the sacredness and divinity of the caste. Ambedkar believed that the real way to annihilate the caste system is

to destroy the belief in the sanctity of the shastras. How do you expect to succeed, if you allow the shastras to continue to mould the beliefs and opinions of the people? Not to question the authority of the shastras, to permit the people to believe in their sanctity and their sanctions and to blame them and criticize them, for their acts as being irrational and inhuman, is an incongruous way of carrying on social reform. Reformers working for the removal of untouchability including Mahatma Gandhi, do not seem to realize that the acts of the people are merely the results of their beliefs inculcated upon their minds by the shastras and that people will not change their conduct until they cease to believe in the sanctity of the shastras on which their conduct is founded’ (Ambedkar 1979: 68).

Ambedkar further added that the caste system has two aspects—it divides men into separate communities, and it places the communities in a graded order, one above the other, as discussed earlier. The higher the grade of a caste is, the greater the number of religious and social rights. Now, this gradation makes it impossible to organize a common front against the caste system. Castes form a graded system of sovereignties, high and low, who are jealous of their status and know that if a general dissolution happened, some of them would lose more prestige and power than others. It is, therefore, not possible to organize a mobilization of the Hindus (Ambedkar 1987(c)).

Can you appeal to reason and ask the Hindus to discard caste as being contrary to reason? Here, Ambedkar quotes Manu: ‘So far as caste and varna are concerned, not only the shastras do not permit the Hindu to use his reason in the decision of the question, but they have taken care to see that no occasion is left to examine in a rational way the foundations of his belief in caste and varna’ (Ambedkar 1979:73). Ambedkar argues that if one wanted to dismantle the caste system, then one would have to implement laws to change the caste system. He proposes the following reforms within the Hindu religion in order to dismantle the caste system:

(i) There should be one and only one standard book of Hindu religion, acceptable to all Hindus and recognized by all Hindus; (ii) It would be appropriate if priesthood among Hindus was abolished, failing which the priesthood should at least cease to be hereditary. Every person who professes to be a Hindu performs rituals as a priest unless he has passed an examination prescribed by the state and holds permission from the state to practice; (iii) no ceremony performed by a priest who does not hold the permission would be deemed to be valid in law, and a person who officiates as a priest without the permission should be penalized; (iv) a priest should be the servant of the state and should be subject to the disciplinary action by the state in the matter of his morals, beliefs; and (v) the number of priests should be limited by law according to the requirements of the state (Ambedkar 1979: 77).

These, according to Ambedkar, would provide the basis for the establishment of a new social order based on liberty, equality and fraternity, in short, with democracy.

Having analysed the exploitative nature of the Hindu social order born out of varnas, castes and sub-castes, Ambedkar gives his own vision of an ideal social order. He looked forward to a society based on liberty, equality and fraternity. Fraternity creates more channels for association and sharing experiences; this helps in establishing an attitude of respect and reverence among individuals towards fellowmen. For Ambedkar, liberty benefits the people by giving them freedom of choice of occupation. Lastly, we need equality because we are aware that all men are not equal in terms of their physical and economic endowments. They are not equal on the basis of parental care, education, accumulation of scientific knowledge and finally, in their own efforts. Therefore, against an individualistic standpoint, Ambedkar emphasized the point that ‘. . . we should make people as equal as far as possible at the very start of the race’ (Ambedkar 1979: 57-78). Second, he reiterates that ‘Statesmen . . . must follow some rough and ready rule and that rough and ready rule is to treat all men alike not because they are alike but because classification and assortment is impossible’ (ibid.). We will discuss this issue in Chapter 3 in detail. Hence, we can see how Ambedkar envisaged a democratic society by annihilating caste.

CONCLUSION

To conclude, we can argue that Ambedkar has propounded a very novel theoretical and philosophical perspective of Hindu social order, which comprises the place of the individual, varna and caste system in a hierarchical manner.

This social order should be first analysed at the varna level, then at the caste and last, how to annihilate it. We also come to know that inequality in the Hindu social order is not simple inequality, as has been explained by other social scientists; rather, it is graded inequality. This is the original idea of Ambedkar. Further, his proposition that castes exist as a system rather than an independent unit is also unique. His philosophical and anthropological explanation of the origin of caste with ‘surplus men’, ‘surplus women’ and the imposition of endogamy over exogamy is an exceptional insight. Further, quoting sociologist Tarde’s law of imitation as the reason for the spread of the caste system, Ambedkar has opened a new vantage point for research in this area. With all these propositions, conceptualizations and formulations, Dr. Ambedkar has presented himself as a sociologist par excellence. On this basis, he can be called one of the founders of Indian sociology.

In the same vein, we have also observed that according to Ambedkar, the caste system is an oppressive, exploitative system that restricts opportunities and creates imbalances and inequalities, and therefore, he thinks it should be annihilated. Ambedkar suggested inter-caste marriage, questioning the sanctity of the sacred texts of the Hindu social order, which provides legitimacy to the structure of caste and abolition of the institution of traditional priesthood as some of the measures for annihilating the caste system in India. Ambedkar concludes by emphasizing the fact that, ‘in my opinion only when the Hindu society becomes a casteless society it can hope to have strength to defend itself’ (Ambedkar 1979: 80). Therefore, for Ambedkar caste was not only a project for emancipation of the Dalits but it was also for strengthening the nation as well.

REFERENCES

Ambedkar, B.R., 1979, Dr. Babasaheb Ambedkar Writings and Speeches, vol. I, Education Department, Government of Maharashtra, Mumbai.

——, 1987(c), Dr. Babasaheb Ambedkar Writings and Speeches, vol. 3, Education Department, Government of Maharashtra, Mumbai.